<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="faqs.xsl" type="text/xml"?>

<faq xml:lang="en">

<section id="install">
<title>Installing ChatZilla</title>
<entry id="install">
<question>
  How do I install ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>ChatZilla is currently distributed as part of the Mozilla Suite, the
    SeaMonkey Suite, and is available as an extension for Mozilla Firefox.
  </p>
  <tip><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/extensions/moreinfo.php?id=16">Get
    ChatZilla here</a>, for Mozilla, SeaMonkey and Firefox.
  </tip>
  <ul>
    <li>If you download the
      <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/releases/">latest Mozilla release</a> or
      the <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/seamonkey/">latest SeaMonkey
      release</a>, you must select <b>Full</b> or <b>Custom</b> when installing
      to get ChatZilla.
    </li>
    <li>If you use Mozilla Firefox, or wish to add ChatZilla to your existing
      Mozilla or SeaMonkey install, you can install the latest version from the
      <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/extensions/moreinfo.php?id=16">Mozilla
      Update site</a>.  Current and older versions may be found on the
      <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/">ChatZilla Development
      page</a>, too.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <note>On all platforms, you will need to restart your browser after
    installing. If you are using the Quick Launch feature of Mozilla or
    SeaMonkey, you will need to exit the quick launch icon on your taskbar as
    well, and on <i>some</i> systems, you may need to restart the operating
    system.
  </note>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="uninstall">
<question>
  How do I uninstall ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>Mozilla Firefox can uninstall extensions such as ChatZilla as follows:
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>Open <menu>Tools<submenu/>Extensions</menu>.
    </li>
    <li>Find the ChatZilla extension, and select it.
    </li>
    <li>Either click the Uninstall button, or right-click and select Uninstall.
    </li>
    <li>Confirm that you want to uninstall ChatZilla, then you need to restart
        Mozilla Firefox to complete the uninstall.
    </li>
  </ol>
  <p>Mozilla and SeaMonkey do not have an uninstall feature for XPIs, but
    removing ChatZilla is usually possible.
  </p>
  <warning>The following manual uninstall procedure is provided with no
    warranty whatsoever.
  </warning>
  <ol>
    <li>Shut down Mozilla or SeaMonkey.
    </li>
    <li>Find (in the application install directory) and rename the files
      <tt>components/chatzilla-service.js</tt>
      and <tt>chrome/chatzilla.jar</tt> to something else.
    </li>
    <li>Run <tt>regchrome</tt>.
    </li>
    <li>If Mozilla starts up fine, everything worked, otherwise, unrename
      everything and give up, or delete the installation and start from
      scratch.
    </li>
  </ol>
</answer> 
</entry>

<entry id="update-in-seamonkey">
<question>
  How do I update ChatZilla to a different version in SeaMonkey on Linux/BSD?
</question>
<answer>
  <p>In SeaMonkey, ChatZilla will need to update some files which are in the
  application directory (usually this is <tt>/usr/local/seamonkey</tt>). This
  directory is normally only writable by root, which will cause problems if you
  run SeaMonkey normally. You are advised to <strong>temporarily</strong> make
  yourself the owner of this directory (for example using the <tt>chown</tt>
  tool) and then run SeaMonkey normally, install the update, restart SeaMonkey,
  and check everything works. After making sure everything is OK, make sure you
  set root to be the owner of the installation directory again.</p>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="default-ircurls">
<question>
  How do I make irc: urls work with my default IRC client instead of ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>If you are using the Mozilla Suite or SeaMonkey, you will need to use the
    uninstall procedure outlined above. If you are using Mozilla Firefox, you
    can disable the ChatZilla extension using the following steps:
  </p>
  <ol>
    <li>Open <menu>Tools<submenu/>Extensions</menu>.
    </li>
    <li>Select ChatZilla from the list of Extensions.
    </li>
    <li>Right-click ChatZilla, and select Disable.
    </li>
    <li>Restart Mozilla Firefox to actually disable ChatZilla.
    </li>
  </ol>
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="start">
<title>Getting Started</title>

<entry id="start-cz">
<question>
  How do I start ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <ul>
    <li>In Mozilla Suite or SeaMonkey, <menu>Window<submenu/>IRC Chat</menu>.
    </li>
    <li>In Mozilla Firefox, <menu>Tools<submenu/>ChatZilla</menu>.
    </li>
    <li>In Mozilla Firefox, you can also place an <b>ChatZilla</b> button on
      your toolbar.
    </li>
    <li>You can also start the browser with the <tt>-chat</tt> command line
      option.  This will launch ChatZilla instead of a browser front end.
    </li>
    <li>You can type an IRC URL in the URL bar. Type just <tt>irc:</tt>
      to launch ChatZilla and connect to your default channels.
      <tip>You can bookmark this URL, and file it wherever it makes sense
        to you.
      </tip>
    </li>
    <li>Of course, you can use any IRC URL to start ChatZilla and make it
      connect to the specified location, however, the default channels will
      not be joined for anything other than <tt>irc:</tt>.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <note>In some rare occasions, a bug in the Mozilla Firefox extension
    manager will disable the ChatZilla extension right after installing, even
    though the item does not show disabled in the list. If you can not start
    ChatZilla as described above (for example, you may get a message saying the
    IRC protocol is not registered), try disabling ChatZilla, restarting
    Firefox, re-enabled ChatZilla, and restarting Firefox again.
  </note>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="connect">
<question>
  How do I connect to a network or server?
</question>

<answer>
  <a name="network"></a>
  <p>ChatZilla comes preset with a selection of popular IRC networks, which
    can be listed via the <tt>/networks</tt> command. The network names can be
    clicked to connect to them, or the <tt>/attach</tt> command can be used.
  </p>
  <tip>ChatZilla allows you to be connected to multiple servers at once, so,
    unlike some other clients, connecting to a new network or server will not
    disconnect you from your current network or server.  You can manually do
    that with the <tt>/disconnect</tt> command.
  </tip>
  <input>/networks</input>
  <output>
    Available networks are [dalnet, efnet, freenode, hybridnet, moznet,
    quakenet, serenia, slashnet, undernet, webbnet].
  </output>
  <input>/attach moznet</input>
  <output>
    Network view for moznet opened.<br/>
    Attempting to connect to moznet. Use /cancel to abort.<br/>
    Connecting to irc://moznet/ (irc://irc.mozilla.org/), attempt 1 of 5...<br/>
    <i>Messages about connecting, and the "message of the day" (MOTD).</i><br/>
    End of /MOTD command.
  </output>
  <a name="server"></a>
  <p>There is no reason you have to use only the networks provided by
    ChatZilla - you can connect to any IRC server you like using the
    <tt>/server</tt> command. For example, other ways to connect to the
    Mozilla IRC Network are (the last one uses a secure connection):
  </p>
  <input>
    /server irc.mozilla.org<br/>
    /server irc.mozilla.org 6667<br/>
    /sslserver irc.mozilla.org 6697
  </input>
  <a name="attach"></a>
  <p>The more general <tt>/attach</tt> command accepts an
    <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/irc-urls.html">irc: URL</a>
    as a parameter.  You may omit the <tt>irc://</tt> prefix, however.  This
    can be used to connect to a network and channel with a single command,
    such as <tt>/attach moznet/chatzilla</tt>, or
    <tt>/attach moznet/killer,isnick</tt>.
  </p>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="proxy">
<question>
  How do I use a proxy with ChatZilla?
</question>
<answer>
  <p>ChatZilla will work automatically with most configurations as it runs
    with your browser's networking configuration. There are four main
    configurations you can use:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><strong>SOCKS v4/v5 proxy:</strong> simply configure your browser's
      SOCKS proxy setting. ChatZilla will use this proxy by default.
    </li>
    <li><strong>HTTP proxy:</strong> make sure your browser has an HTTP proxy
      configured, and then set "http" as the <em>Proxy Type</em>.
    </li>
    <li><strong>Force no proxy:</strong> if you have a SOCKS proxy in the
      browser for something else and don't want ChatZilla to use it, set
      "none" as the <em>Proxy Type</em>.
    </li>
    <li><strong>No proxy at all:</strong> with no SOCKS proxy set in your
      browser, ChatZilla will by default use direct connections. This is the
      normal mode of operation as is set by leaving <em>Proxy Type</em> empty.
    </li>
  </ul>
  <p>The <em>Proxy Type</em> setting is found in ChatZilla's Preferences
    window, on the General tab in the Connection group. It exists both for
    Global Settings and for each network. It is only available in
    <b>ChatZilla 0.9.75</b> and later.
  </p>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="connect-issues">
<question>
  What do I do if I get an error connecting?
</question>
<answer>
  <p>First, don't panic. It all depends on the error.  The most common reasons
    are the wrong address for the server, or a firewall mis-configuration.
    The following list will hopefully cover the error you have, but if you
    are getting a different error try to connect to
    <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/chatzilla">#chatzilla</a> on
    <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/">irc.mozilla.org</a> and we'll help you
    resolve the problem.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><a name="connection.unknown.host"><output>Unknown host ``irc.example.com'' connecting to irc://irc.example.com/ (irc.example.com:6667).</output></a>
      <p>This error means that ChatZilla could not find the physical server for
        the name given.  It is most likely that the <b>server name specified is
        not correct</b>, although it could be a problem with the DNS
        configuration for the server's host or a local DNS problem.  Try going
        to the website for the server or network, if you can find one, and
        check that the name you used is correct.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li><a name="connection.timeout"><output>Connection to irc://irc.example.com/ (irc.example.com:6667) timed out.</output></a>
      <p>This error means that the server's address was found, but it did not
        respond when contacted.  A possible reason for this is that your
        anti-virus software or firewall software is configured to block IRC.
        If you have no firewall, or disabling it does not help, the IRC server
        is probably down.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li><a name="connection.refused"><output>Connection to irc://irc.example.com/ (irc.example.com:6667) refused.</output></a>
      <p>This error means that the server <i>was</i> found, but it did not wish
        to let you connect.  This could be because the wrong port (6667 in this
        example) was used; verify that the server is not on a different port
        (especially if you are trying to connect using SSL) and try again.  This
        error could also mean that the server is having a temporary technical
        problem.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li><a name="connection.closed"><output>Connection to irc://irc.example.com/ (irc.example.com:6667) closed.</output></a>
      <p>This error means that the connection was closed before it could be
        properly connected.  The most likely reason for this is that your
        anti-virus software or firewall software is configured to block IRC.
      </p>
      <p><b>ZoneAlarm Internet Security</b> is known to block IRC like this;
        you can fix this by going to IMSecurity &gt; Settings &gt; Advanced
        and un-ticking the "Block IRC" option.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li><a name="connection.reset"><output>Connection to irc://irc.example.com/ (irc.example.com:6667) reset.</output></a>
      <p>This error means that ChatZilla was able to open the connection
        initially, but the connection was then closed unexpectedly.
        The most likely reason for this is that your anti-virus software or
        firewall software is configured to block IRC.
      </p>
      <p><b>McAfee Anti-Virus</b> is known to do this and you will need to
        unblock the IRC ports to use any IRC client; you can do this from the
        "Access Protection" area in the "VirusScan Console" by disabling the
        rules for ports 6666-6669. Consult your anti-virus program's
        documentation for instructions on how to do this for other anti-virus
        programs.
      </p>
      <p>Although less common, any computer between you and the server can
        cause this error, so it could just be a reset or reboot of your DSL
        router, or a local network configuration change.  In these cases,
        the error should only be temporary, and you will be able to try to
        connect again in a few seconds (ChatZilla should retry for you).
      </p>
    </li>
    <li><output>ERROR Closing Link: irc.example.com (Install IdentD)</output>
      <p>This message, sometimes worded differently (but will always mentioning
        "ident" or "identd"), means that the server you tried to connect to
        requires a <a href="#ident">special identification service</a>.
      </p>
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="ident">
<question>
  How do I enable 'ident'?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>Some servers will require you to be running an "ident server" to connect
    to them, even though this service is only useful if you run a multi-user
    computer (where many people can connect and share a single computer).
  </p>
  <p>In ChatZilla 0.9.71 and later, you can check the "Enable Identification
    Server during connection process" box in Preferences, or enter the command
    <kbd>/network-pref identd.enabled true</kbd> to enable ChatZilla's ident
    server for the current network.
  </p>
  <note>Ident servers listen on TCP port 113. This may mean you need to
    open/forward this port on any NAT devices or firewalls you use.
  </note>
  <note>On some operating systems, such as Linux and Mac OS X, ident servers
    must instead run as part of the system. You should consult your system's
    documentation for more information.
  </note>
  <tip>Some networks only have a few servers that require ident. Trying
    specific servers may let you connect without ident.
  </tip>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="join">
<question>
  How do I join a channel?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>Once you have <a href="#connect">connected to a server</a>, you can join a
    channel by using the <tt>/join</tt> command.  For example, if you have
    connected to <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/">MozNet</a>, you can join the
    ChatZilla channel.
  </p>
  <input>
    /join #chatzilla
  </input>
  <output>
    Channel view for #chatzilla opened.<br/>
    YOU (NickName) have joined #chatzilla<br/>
    Topic for #chatzilla is "<b>ChatZilla -- LATEST VERSION</b> is 0.9.68.5.1"<br/>
    Topic for #chatzilla was set by Somebody on 22 September 2005 16:37:05
  </output>
  <tip>Unsure what channels there are on a particular server? Just connect, and
    select <menu>IRC<submenu/>Join Channel...</menu> and browse through the
    <a href="#list">list of channels</a>.
  </tip>
  <tip>The command <tt>/j</tt> is an alias (shortcut) for <tt>/join</tt>.</tip>
  <p>If you omit a channel type prefix (e.g. <tt>#</tt>, <tt>&amp;</tt>,
    <tt>+</tt> or <tt>!</tt>) ChatZilla will prepend the network's default
    prefix. This is usually <tt>#</tt>, but can vary. If you'd like to check,
    run the <tt>/supports</tt> command and see what character is listed first
    for "Supported channel types:".
  </p>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="list">
<question>
  How can I list the available channels on a server?
</question>

<answer>
  Use <menu>IRC<submenu/>Join channel...</menu> to open a dialog that will
  list all channels on the current network.  You can join an existing channel
  or create a new channel from this dialog, filter channels by name, topic, and
  exclude channels with more, or less, than a certain number of users.  On
  large networks, however, this dialog may have difficulty operating (20,000
  channels is about its limit, due to limitations in JavaScript).

  <note>This dialog was added in ChatZilla <b>0.9.67</b> and is not available
  in earlier versions.</note>

  The <code>/list</code> command can be used to fetch a list of all channels on
  the current network.  On large networks, however, this may take a very long
  time.  On some networks, you'll be kicked off with a message like ``Excess
  Flood'' for doing this.  Adding to the confusion, some networks recognize
  extended <code>/list</code> options for filtering based on number of
  users in a channel, etc. (if you need such features, try the join dialog
  mentioned above).
  <p/>
  ChatZilla also offers an <code>/rlist</code> command, which can be used to
  filter the result list based on the channel name, regardless of the
  server software.  Type <code>/help rlist</code> for more information.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="lights">
<question>
  What do the symbols/blobs in the user list mean?
</question>
<answer>
  The blobs are supposed to resemble lights. They indicate each user's status
  in the channel.
  <ul>
    <li><strong>No symbol/black</strong>: Normal - the user has no special
        status.
    </li>
    <li><strong>+/grey</strong>: Voice - the user can talk in the channel when
        it is moderated. Often used to mark people as trusted without giving
        them power.
    </li>
    <li><strong>%/blue</strong>: Halfop - the user has the power to moderate the
        channel, change the topic, etc., but cannot kick other halfops nor
        higher-ranking users, nor can he/she create new ops/halfops. Not all
        servers support halfops.
    </li>
    <li><strong>@/green</strong>: Op - the user can grant/revoke op/halfop/voice
        status, and change other channel settings, depending on the server.
    </li>
    <li><strong>&amp;/orange</strong> and <strong>~/purple</strong>: Channel
        Admin/Founder - ranks above op, usually assigned by network services.
        Their exact behaviour varies depending on server.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="disconnect">
<question>
  How do I disconnect from a server?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>To disconnect from a single network without exiting ChatZilla, right-click
    a tab from the network and select the <menu>Disconnect From</menu> option,
    or switch to a view on the network and use the
    <menu>IRC<submenu/>Disconnect From</menu> menu item.  You can also type
    <tt>/disconnect</tt> on any view associated with the network.
  </p>
  <tip>To disconnect from all networks without exiting ChatZilla, type
    <tt>/disconnect-all</tt>.
  </tip>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="hide-ip">
<question>
  How can I hide my IP address from other users?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>In general you can't.  The way IRC works, your IP address is distributed to
    every user you communicate with.  Depending on where you hang out, and who
    your enemies are, this may or may not be a problem.  In practice, it's not a
    problem for most normal users.
  </p>
  <p>However, an increasing number of servers are supporting a user mode
    "<tt>x</tt>" which hides your hostname (and thus your IP) from other users
    (IRC Operators can still see your real host, however). You can start using
    this user mode by adding "<tt>x</tt>" to the Usermode box on the General tab
    in preferences, either in <b>Global Settings</b>, or for individual servers.
  </p>
  <note>Remember that not all servers support this. Ones that don't will
    simply ignore it, so don't worry about adding it if you're not sure.
  </note>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="dcc">
<question>
  How do I use DCC to transfer files with ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <p>ChatZilla currently has a basic implementation of DCC Chat and DCC File.
    The following is a summary of the commands and how to use it, enter 
    <tt>/help dcc</tt> into ChatZilla for more information.
  </p>
  <note>A couple of commonly requested DCC features are Resume and Reverse
    support.  ChatZilla currently does <b>not</b> support either of these,
    but they are both planned for a version in the future.
  </note>
  <div class="figure">
    <table class="figure-contents" cellpadding="2px">
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/dcc-chat nickname</code></td>
        <td>
          Sends a DCC Chat offer to <tt>nickname</tt>, which they can then 
          accept or decline.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/dcc-send nickname</code></td>
        <td>
          Prompts you to pick a file to send to <tt>nickname</tt>, after which
          it sends the offer. The other user can then accept or decline this 
          offer.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/dcc-accept</code></td>
        <td>
          Accepts the last DCC Chat or DCC File offer made to you. This will 
          not work within 10 seconds of an offer arriving, during which time 
          you may accept the offer using the slightly longer command of 
          <tt>/dcc-accept nickname</tt>.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/dcc-decline</code></td>
        <td>
          Declines (refuses) the last DCC Chat or DCC File offer made to you.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/dcc-accept-list</code>,
          <code>/dcc-accept-list-add</code>,
          <code>/dcc-accept-list-remove</code></td>
        <td>
          Manages the DCC auto-accept list. DCC Chat or DCC File offers from
          users on this list will be automatically accepted.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
      Direct Client Connection commands
  </div>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="charset">
<question>
  How do I select a character set? (and why can't other users read my text?)
</question>

<answer>
  <p>ChatZilla allows you to select character encodings at multiple levels.
    The default character encoding used by ChatZilla is UTF-8, and it is
    recommended that you leave this setting wherever possible.  This default
    avoids a number of unsolvable problems, such as how to know what encoding
    has been used for particular channel names without prior knowledge.
  </p>
  <tip>The most common character encoding is ISO-8859-15, since this is what
    mIRC normally uses (it can also do Shift-JIS for Japanese). If you are
    unsure, or other members of the channel are clueless, try using ISO-8859-15
    first (type <tt>/charset ISO-8859-15</tt> on the channel view).
  </tip>
  <p>An unfortunate problem with the way IRC works is that international (and
    most non-US-ASCII) characters cannot be sent without encoding them.  The
    problem is that there are many, many different character encodings
    available, and different systems and programs use different ones.  To help
    alleviate this problem, ChatZilla supports many different character
    encodings, and lets you select the right one for each channel and server.
  </p>
  <p>If text is showing up with a lot of question-marks (?) or completely
    unexpected characters (for example, Japanese characters in a Danish channel)
    then it is likely that ChatZilla is not using the same charset as the other
    client(s).  The table below lists the charset commands available in
    ChatZilla. Each of these commands takes a case-insensitive character
    encoding name as a parameter.  If a character encoding is not provided,
    these commands will display the current setting.  If you pass a dash ("-")
    as the character encoding name, the setting will revert to the default
    character encoding.
  </p>
  <div class="figure">
    <table class="figure-contents" cellpadding="2px">
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/default-charset</code></td>
        <td>
          Selects the default character encoding for all networks, channels,
          and users.  This charset is used when no other more specific charset 
          preference has been set.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/charset</code></td>
        <td>
          Selects the character encoding for the current view, and works from
          all views.  When changing the network charset all channels and query
          views will inherit the value unless it is set on the specific
          channel or query views.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
      Character encoding commands.
  </div>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="log">
<question>
  How do I enable logging?
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla logging can be enabled at a number of levels.  The most
  straightforward way to turn on logging for a specific view is to
  type <tt>/log on</tt> from the view in question.
  
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <ul>
        <li>To log the current view, type
            <tt>/log on</tt>, type <tt>/log off</tt> to stop logging.
        </li>
        <li>To log all channel views by default, type
            <tt>/pref channelLog true</tt>.
        </li>
        <li>To log all network views by default, type
            <tt>/pref networkLog true</tt>.
        </li>
        <li>To log all query views by default, type
            <tt>/pref userLog true</tt>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
    Logging related preferences
  </div>

  Note that you may override any of the defaults by using the <tt>/log</tt>
  command on the view in question.
  <p/>
  By default, ChatZilla stores logs in the <tt>logs/</tt> subdirectory of your
  ChatZilla profile path.  Type <tt>/pref logFileName</tt> to see where this
  is.  You may modify the logFileName pref, but it will not copy over your old
  logs.
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="basic-usage">
<title>Basic Usage</title>

<entry id="nick-complete">
<question>
  Does ChatZilla have nickname completion?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  Type enough of a person's nickname to make it unique and press the
  <b>tab</b> key.
  <p/>
  If the name is not unique, ChatZilla will append any characters that it
  has in common with other matching nicknames.  If you press <b>tab</b> twice,
  quickly, then ChatZilla will display all matching nicknames.
  <p/>
  From network and query views, you can tab complete on any nickname in
  any channel on the same network.  From channel views, only users in the
  same channel will be included in the tab completion.  In addition to
  nicknames, you can tab complete any channel you are on (or have been on) on
  the same network.
  
  <tip>To complete the current channel name, type only the character "#",
  press the <b>tab</b> key, and ChatZilla will expand it.</tip>
  
  There is a default tab completion for channel tabs.  If you press
  <b>tab</b> on an empty line, ChatZilla will match the last person to
  trigger your <a href="#stalk">stalk</a> function.
  
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">

  Assuming that <i>rginda_home</i> and <i>rginda_work</i> are members
  of the current channel:

  <ol>
    <li>Type <tt>rg</tt> and press <b>tab</b>.  ChatZilla responds by
        completing <tt>rginda_</tt>.  ChatZilla stops completing here, because
        there are two nicknames that start with these characters.
    </li>
    <li>Press <b>tab</b> twice, quickly.  ChatZilla responds by displaying the
        message ``2 matches for &#8220;rginda_&#8221;:
        [rginda_home, rginda_work]''.
    </li>
    <li>Add an <tt>h</tt>, and <b>tab</b>.  If this is the first word in
        the textbox, ChatZilla responds by completing
        ``<tt>rginda_home, </tt>''.  If this is <b>not</b> the first word,
        ChatZilla will leave out the comma.
    </li>
   </ol>

   </div>
    Nickname completion<br/>
  </div>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="cmd-complete">
<question>
  Does ChatZilla have command completion?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  It works just like nickname completion.  If the cursor is in the
  first word of the text, and the first character is a forward slash ("/"),
  then ChatZilla will automatically match against commands, instead of
  users or channels.
  
  <tip>You don't actually need to type the entire command name - ChatZilla
  will allow you to shorten the command just enough to make the name
  unique.</tip>
  
  <warning>Some servers and websites suggest you use <tt>/cs</tt> instead of
  <tt>/msg ChanServ</tt>. Please note that this does <b>not</b> work in
  ChatZilla versions <b>before 0.9.79</b>, because they support the
  <tt>/css</tt> command which ChatZilla matches (since <tt>/cs</tt> is
  <b>not</b> a standard IRC command). In ChatZilla 0.9.79, the <tt>/css</tt>
  command was removed, as it was just an alias for <tt>/motif</tt>.</warning>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="copy">
<question>
  Why do some messages appear in the network tab?
</question>

<answer>
  Those messages have been copied there because they matched your 
  <a href="#stalk">stalk</a> list.  The reasoning here is that, if you're
  away from the computer for a long time, important messages might have
  scrolled off the view by the time you get back.  Copying the
  message to the network tab makes sure you don't miss anything important.  It's
  also a quick way to catch up after being away for a while.
  <p/>
  The <menu>View<submenu/>Copy Important Messages</menu> menu item can be used
  to disable this feature.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="timestamps">
<question>
  Where are the timestamps?
</question>
  
<answer>
  Use <menu>View<submenu/>Show Timestamps</menu> to toggle timestamps globally,
  or turn them on by setting the Timestamps options on the Appearance tab in
  preferences, either in <b>Global Settings</b>, or on any other view.
  <p/>
  Timestamps also appear in the statusbar when you mouse over messages.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="conf-mode">
<question>
  Why do some/all channels not show JOIN, PART, QUIT or nick change messages?
</question>

<answer>
  The most likely reason is that ChatZilla has automatically enabled
  "Conference Mode" on these channels, which occurs when the number of users
  exceeds a configurable limit (default is 150 in current versions).
  <p/>
  To check or change the limit, open the ChatZilla preferences window, and check
  the <b>Appearance</b> tab - it is labeled "Conference Mode limit". You can set
  this limit globally (select <b>Global Settings</b> on the left), for a single
  network (select the network), or individual channels.
  <p/>
  Conference Mode is automatically enabled and disabled as the number of users
  changes, but only when the count is at least 10 above or below the configured
  value (to prevent it changing too often on channels near the limit). You can use
  any limit you like, including the special value <b>0</b> for <i>never hiding</i>
  join, part, quit and nick change messages, and <b>1</b> for <i>always
  hiding</i> them.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="stalk">
<question>
  What is a stalk list?
</question>

<answer>
  A stalk list is a list of words or nicknames that you want ChatZilla to
  consider important.  Important messages are treated differently than
  normal messages.  For example:
  <ul>
    <li>The message will likely be styled differently in the message window.
    </li>
    <li>If you have ``Copy Important Messages'' enabled, the message will be
        copied to its associated network view.
    </li>
    <li>The channel's tab label will turn red, if it's not already the
        current tab.
    </li>
    <li>ChatZilla may beep, or play a .wav file.  You can adjust this setting
        through the preferences window.
    </li>
    <li>The ChatZilla window may try to get your attention.  On some platforms
        this is done by flashing an application icon, on others the window
        may come to the front.  You can adjust this setting through the
        preferences window in <b>Global Settings</b>, on the <b>Global</b> tab,
        using the Aggressive notify option.
    </li>
  </ul>
  By default, your nickname is the only entry in your stalk list. You can
  add other words to your stalk list from the <b>Lists</b> tab in <b>Global
  Settings</b>, in preferences.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="channel-key">
<question>
  How can I join a channel that requires a key, at startup?
</question>

<answer>
  From the ChatZilla preferences dialog, select <b>Global Settings</b>, then
  the <b>Startup</b> tab, add a new channel to the autoconnect list, and
  specify the channel name as <tt>channelname?key=keyvalue</tt>.  So, if you
  wanted to join <tt>#cia</tt> on the Mozilla network with the key
  <tt>tenent</tt> at startup, you would specify the item as
  <tt>irc://moznet/cia?key=tenent</tt>.
  
  <note>You can find out more about
  <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/irc-urls.html">irc:
  URLs</a>, which includes how to specify a server password, and how to prompt
  for passwords/keys instead of storing them directly.</note>
  
  <warning>This information is stored as plain text in your preferences
  file.  Anyone with access to your machine will be able to read it.  Do not
  use this method to autojoin if this concerns.</warning>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="colors">
<question>
  How do I use color/bold/underline in my text?
</question>

<answer>
  First of all, you must enable the function - this is to help mark sure 
  you really want colors and aren't just out to annoy people (overly 
  colorful text is a big annoyance to many people). It's usually worth 
  making sure the channel(s) you want to use colors with don't mind, 
  as some channels will kick and possibly ban people who use colors.
  <p/>
  Simply do <code>/pref outgoing.colorCodes true</code> to enable entering
  colors. This setting is saved, so you will only need to do it once.
  <p/>
  To actually  insert colors, bold or underline, you need to enter <tt>%</tt>
  into the input box, then you will get a little popup window reminding you
  what to do. Here is a summary:
  <div class="floating-figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td bgcolor="#000000" class="fg-white">00</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c8c8c8" class="fg-black">01</td>
            <td bgcolor="#0000c8" class="fg-white">02</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00c800" class="fg-white">03</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c80000" class="fg-white">04</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c8c800" class="fg-black">05</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c800c8" class="fg-black">06</td>
            <td bgcolor="#ffb000" class="fg-black">07</td>
          </tr><tr>
            <td bgcolor="#ffff00" class="fg-black">08</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00ff00" class="fg-black">09</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00c8c8" class="fg-black">10</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00ffff" class="fg-black">11</td>
            <td bgcolor="#0000ff" class="fg-white">12</td>
            <td bgcolor="#ff00ff" class="fg-white">13</td>
            <td bgcolor="#808080" class="fg-white">14</td>
            <td bgcolor="#989898" class="fg-white">15</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </div>
    Color Chart
  </div>
  <ul>
    <li><b>%U</b> - toggle underline</li>
    <li><b>%B</b> - toggle bold</li>
    <li><b>%R</b> - swaps foreground and background colors</li>
    <li><b>%O</b> - reverts colors to defaults</li>
    <li><b>%C</b> - sets the text color, e.g. <b>%C4</b> for red text</li>
    <li><b>%%</b> - putting two percent characters before <b>U</b>,
      <b>B</b>, <b>R</b>, <b>O</b> or <b>C</b> stops ChatZilla doing
      anything special with it, so you can still say "%C" by 
      typing <b>%%C</b>.</li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="emoticons">
<question>
  How do I use smilies/emoticons/faces in my text?
</question>

<answer>
  Simple - just type out the smiley you want as you might in an e-mail, and 
  ChatZilla will automatically display an image in its place, just like it 
  does for other people's messages. But what smiles/emoticons are available?
  <p/>
  <table width="100%">
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><tt><b>:-)</b></tt> - happy</td>
        <td><tt><b>:-S</b></tt> - confused</td>
        <td><tt><b>&gt;:-(</b></tt> - angry</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt><b>;-)</b></tt> - winking</td>
        <td><tt><b>B-)</b></tt> - cool</td>
        <td><tt><b>&gt;:-D</b></tt> - evil</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt><b>:-D</b></tt> - very happy/laughing</td>
        <td><tt><b>:")</b></tt> - blushing</td><!-- " -->
        <td><tt><b>o_O</b></tt> - dizzy</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt><b>X-D</b></tt> - laughing hard</td>
        <td><tt><b>:~(</b></tt> - crying</td>
        <td><tt><b>O_O</b></tt> - "eek", wide-eyed</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt><b>:-O</b></tt> - surprised</td>
        <td><tt><b>:-|</b></tt> - flat, undecided</td>
        <td><tt><b>:-?</b></tt> - questioning</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt><b>:-P</b></tt> - tongue out</td>
        <td><tt><b>:-(</b></tt> - sad</td>
        <td><tt><b>9_9</b></tt> - rolling eyes</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p/>
  Most of the emoticons work without the nose (<tt>-</tt>), or with
  <tt>^</tt> or <tt>v</tt> replacing it. Apart from <tt>:-)</tt> and
  <tt>;-)</tt> the <tt>:</tt> may be replaced with <tt>;</tt> or <tt>=</tt>
  too. You can take your pick from these variations, and ChatZilla will still
  know which icon to use - if you want to see what someone else has used,
  hover your mouse over the icon.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="inatab">
<question>
  How do I load ChatZilla in a tab?
</question>

<answer>
  <note>We do not support running ChatZilla in a tab.</note>
  
  To try anyway, enter <tt>chrome://chatzilla/content/</tt> into the location
  bar.
  
  <warning>
    There are some problems with running ChatZilla in a tab, and most are not
    things we can do anything about. Below is a list of what is known to break.
  </warning>
  
  <ul>
    <li>Right-clicking the chat area shows the browser's context menu instead
      of ChatZilla's.
    </li>
    <li>Clicking an <tt>irc:</tt> URL in the chat area will open a separate
      <b>ChatZilla window</b>. This problem <i>might</i> be fixable, but it
      could well be harder to fix than the final point.
    </li>
    <li>Clicking web links in the chat area will usually <b>replace ChatZilla
      with the webpage</b>. If you try to open the link in a new tab or
      window (either from the context menu or using a modifier key), it should
      leave ChatZilla unaffected.
    </li>
    <li>Clicking an <tt>irc:</tt> URL from a webpage will also open a separate
      <b>ChatZilla window</b>, instead of loading it in the ChatZilla running
      in a tab. This is the only problem we believe we can fix.
    </li>
    <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=286651">Bug
      286651</a> is attempting to remove the special permission extensions get
      when loaded in a tab, which would basically be the end of this working
      at all.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry>
<question>
  Why are my tabs sometimes colored red, green or blue?
</question>
<answer>
  The different colors indicate different degrees of activity.
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Black:</strong> There is no new activity. A tab will go back to
        this state when you focus it.
    </li>
    <li><strong>Blue:</strong> The channel changed in some way. This is usually
        caused by people joining or leaving, a mode change or a topic change.
    </li>
    <li><strong>Green:</strong> A message appeared on the tab. The message
        can be a normal chat message, an action, or a notice. Messages sent
        <strong>just</strong> to you will color the tab red instead.
    </li>
    <li><strong>Red:</strong> Someone used your name or something on your
        <a href="#stalk">stalk</a> list in a message on that tab, or someone
        sent a message to you specifically.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>
</section>

<section id="customizing">
<title>Customizing ChatZilla</title>
<entry id="nick">
<question>
  How do I set my nickname?
</question>

<answer>
  When you first connect to a server with ChatZilla, you are prompted to enter
  a nickname.  If you would like to change it later, use the <tt>/nick</tt>
  command.  ChatZilla automatically remembers your last nickname for
  each network you connect to.
  
  <note>In ChatZilla <b>0.9.67</b> and later, when you connect to a network and
  someone else is using your nickname, ChatZilla automatically reclaims it when
  they leave or change nick, but only for the first 6 minutes.</note>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="desc">
<question>
  How do I set my description?
</question>

<answer>
  Your description is a single line of text that other users will see when
  they request information about you.  Many people use it for their full name
  or web site.  Use the <tt>/desc</tt> command to change your description.  The
  description is sent during the login process, so you must reconnect to the
  server for it to take effect.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="autoperform">
<question>
  How do I ``autoperform'' some commands when I connect to a network?
</question>

<answer>
  Each network has an ``autoperform'' preference which consists of a list
  of standard ChatZilla commands.  You can modify this preference with
  the preferences window, and the <tt>/network-pref</tt> command, see the
  example below.
  
  <warning>If you're using this to automatically ``auth'' yourself with a bot
  or service, remember that your password will be stored in <b>plain text</b>
  in your preferences file.</warning>
  
  Autoperform commands are executed when ChatZilla successfully logs in to
  a network, regardless of how the connection was initiated.  The commands are
  executed before attempting to join any ``Open at Startup'' channels, and
  before attempting to re-join any existing tabs associated with that network.
  
  <note>This preference was added in ChatZilla <b>0.9.41</b>.</note>
  
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
To send a message to a user whenever you connect to EFNet, first select any
tab associated with EFNet, then type:<br/>
<br/>
<tt class="indent">/network-pref autoperform msg WiZ here I am again</tt><br/>
<br/>
You may separate multiple commands with the semicolon (';') character, as
 in:<br/>
<br/>
<tt class="indent">/network-pref autoperform msg WiZ yo; msg mozbot trees</tt>
<br/>
<br/>
    </div>
    Setting up autoperform commands
  </div>
  <p/>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="reconnect">
<question>
  How do I prevent ChatZilla from auto-reconnecting to a network?
</question>

<answer>
  By default, ChatZilla will reconnect to a network if you are forcibly
  disconnected.  On networks with idle time limits, this can earn you a
  temporary ban.
  <p/>
  If you would like to turn this off by default, type
  <tt>/pref reconnect false</tt>.  If you would like to turn it off only
  for a particular network, type <tt>/network-pref reconnect false</tt> from
  any tab associated with the network in question.
  <p/>
  Note that if you change the default to <tt>false</tt>, you can still
  override specific networks with the <tt>/network-pref</tt> command.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="rejoin">
<question>
  How do I make ChatZilla auto-rejoin a channel when I'm kicked?
</question>

<answer>
  By default, ChatZilla will not try to rejoin a channel if you are kicked 
  from it. You can turn this on globally using <tt>/pref autoRejoin true</tt>,
  or <tt>/channel-pref autoRejoin true</tt> to turn it on only for the 
  current channel (see <a href="#prefs">tweaking the preferences</a> for more
  details).
  
  <warning>Be careful on which channels you enable this, as some bots
  and channel operators will ban people who auto-rejoin when kicked.</warning>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="font-size">
<question>
  How do I set the font size?
</question>

<answer>
  <div class="floating-figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td><i>Control - +</i></td>
            <td>Make text bigger by 2pt</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><i>Control - &#150;</i></td>
            <td>Make text smaller by 2pt</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><i>Control - 0</i></td>
            <td>Reset to browser-default</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </div>
    Summary of Shortcuts
  </div>
  If your fonts are way too large or way too small, it is likely a problem with
  your DPI setting.  Check your display preferences.  If you're set to use
  "System Setting", try one of the pre-defined DPI settings instead.  In
  practice, it seems that "System Setting" is almost always wrong.  Fixing this
  will likely help out with web pages that specify font sizes in points, too.
  <p/>
  If it's not a DPI thing, you can use the options in the menu under 
  <menu>View<submenu/>Font Family and Size</menu>. The options include some
  useful shortcuts (see table to the right) as well as the option to enter a
  size and font name explicitly. <tt>Small</tt>, <tt>Medium</tt> and 
  <tt>Large</tt> are based on the browser's base font size, and the three
  font options (<tt>Serif</tt>, <tt>Sans Serif</tt> and <tt>Monospace</tt>) 
  use the appropriate browser-configured fonts as well.
  <p/>
  For those less inclined to use menus, the commands <tt>/font-size</tt> and
  <tt>/font-family</tt> provide the same functionality. The former accepts the
  text values "default", "small", "medium", "large", "smaller" and "bigger"
  which have the obvious meanings from the menu. The latter command accepts
  the special names "serif", "sans-serif" and "monospace". Both accept other
  values, either the font size in points (pt), or the font family name.
  <p/>
  All these options affect all views in ChatZilla. This doesn't mean you can't
  be awkward and have different sizes or fonts on different views - just use the
  commands described in the <a href="#prefs">preferences</a> entry, and the
  pref names "font.size" and "font.family". For example, if you wanted to make
  the current network use 12pt text instead of the default, you would do 
  <tt>/network-pref font.size 12</tt>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="set-motif">
<question>
  How do I change the color scheme of the message window?
</question>
<answer>
  From the <menu>View<submenu/>Color Scheme</menu> menu.  ChatZilla comes
  with three color schemes, known as "motifs".  <b>Default Motif</b> uses your
  default fore and background colors, and specifies no colors of its own.
  <b>Dark Motif</b> is a dark background on white text, with some appropriate
  colors
  for various message types.  <b>Light Motif</b> is the opposite, using
  white as the background color, and black for message text.
  <p/>
  The <tt>/motif</tt> command can be used to select a CSS file by means of an
  ordinary http: or file: URL.  For example, the command
  <tt>/motif http://example.host.com/cool-color-scheme.css</tt> would be used
  to select the "cool-color-scheme.css" motif from "example.host.com".
  <p/>
  You may also use <tt>/network-motif</tt>, <tt>/channel-motif</tt>, and
  <tt>/user-motif</tt> commands to set a motif for a particular tab, or
  group of tabs.  See the <a href="#multiple-motifs">multiple motifs
  question</a> for more information.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="alias">
<question>
  How do I use aliases? (or make new commands)
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla has some extensive <a href="#scripts">scripting</a> support,
  however, not everyone wants or needs so much power. Aliases provide this
  "watered down" power, by letting you quickly and simply create a new command
  that performs a set of other commands (which may themselves be aliases).
  <p/>
  In its simplest form, an alias is simply renaming a command and fixing some
  parameters:
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <tt class="indent">/alias moz attach moznet</tt>
    </div>
    Creates a simple alias called "moz" to connect to MozNet. Running
    <tt>/moz</tt> will execute the alias.
  </div>
  <p/>
  You can run multiple commands by separating them with semi-colons (<tt>;</tt>):
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <tt class="indent">/alias mychannels join #chatzilla; join #venkman;
        join #xul; join #js</tt>
    </div>
    Creates a multi-command alias called "mychannels". Running
    <tt>/mychannels</tt> will join "#chatzilla", "#venkman", "#xul" and "#js"
    on the current network.
  </div>
  <p/>
  Often, you want to shorten a command - or run a collection of commands -
  using some variable input. Aliases can use as many parameters as you like,
  and may be referenced using <tt>$(param key)</tt> notation. There are a few
  different parameter keys available:
  <div class="figure">
    <table class="figure-contents" width="100%">
      <tr>
        <th>Syntax</th>
        <th>Explanation</th>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt>$(N)</tt></td>
        <td>Gets the parameter at position N, with 1 being the first. The parameter is required to run the alias.</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt>$(N+)</tt></td>
        <td>Gets the parameter at position N, and all those following it. Only parameter N is required.</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt>$(M-N)</tt></td>
        <td>Gets parameter M through N, inclusive. All parameters from M to N, inclusive, are required.</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt>$(all)</tt></td>
        <td>Gets all parameters. This is similar to <tt>$(1+)</tt>, but does not require any parameters.</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt>$(recip)</tt></td>
        <td>Gets the name of the target of the alias. This is the name of the view running the alias, e.g. channel name.</td>
      </tr><tr>
        <td><tt>$(nick)</tt></td>
        <td>Gets the user's current nickname.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
  <p/>
  For this example, the command will use IRC Services "NickServ" to reclaim
  your registered nickname. When run, it ghosts the nickname (a feature of
  NickServ which kicks them off the server if you know their password -
  useful when you've just had to reconnect and your old self is still
  there), changes to your normal nickname, and identifies with NickServ.
  The first parameter is your normal nickname, and the second is the password
  for that nickname.
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <tt class="indent">/alias reclaim msg nickserv ghost $(1) $(2); nick
        $(1); msg nickserv identify $(2)</tt>
    </div>
    Creates a command alias called "reclaim" which requires two parameters.
  </div>
  <p/>
  At their most complicated, you can use JavaScript in aliases via the
  <tt>/eval</tt> command. These are easily harmful to ChatZilla if you get
  anything wrong (and sometimes even if you don't!), so we advise you join
  <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/chatzilla">#chatzilla</a> if you need any
  help with this.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="faces-motif">
<question>
  How do I show faces in ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  There is a motif available that displays pictures next to the nicknames
  of many of the moznet people.  You can find information on
  how to use this motif at the
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/faces.pl">moznet faces</a>
  page on hacksrus.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="timestamp-format">
<question>
  How do I change the timestamp format?
</question>

<answer>
  The timestamp format is controlled by the <tt>timestampFormat</tt> 
  preference, which you can set globally, per network, or even individually 
  on channels and query views (see <a href="#prefs">tweaking the 
  preferences</a>).
  <p/>
  The format string is displayed literally, except for the following 6 
  substrings, which get replaced as follows:
  <ul>
    <li><b>%y</b> - 4 digit year.
    </li>
    <li><b>%m</b> - month number (1 - 12).
    </li>
    <li><b>%d</b> - day of the month.
    </li>
    <li><b>%h</b> - hour, in 24-hour format.
    </li>
    <li><b>%n</b> - minutes.
    </li>
    <li><b>%s</b> - seconds.
    </li>
 </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="multiple-motifs">
<question>
  Can I use different color schemes for different channels?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  The <tt>/network-motif</tt>, <tt>/channel-motif</tt>, and
  <tt>/user-motif</tt> commands can be used to choose a motif for a
  particular tab or group of tabs.  For example, you might use a
  <a href="#faces-mofit">faces motif</a> on the moznet network, but a "plain"
  motif for dalnet.
  <p/>
  If you've got some web space (no CGI required) you can publish a
  <a href="#make-motif">CSS file</a> specially tailored to your channel.
  This could be as easy as picking a custom background image and a
  matching color scheme.  (You will also need to host any images.)
  Users can try out your motif by typing one of the <tt>/*-motif</tt>
  commands listed above, followed by the URL to the CSS file on your web site.
  Users may also drag a link to a CSS file into the ChatZilla message area, to
  use that file as the <b>default</b> motif.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="make-motif">
<question>
  How do I make my own color scheme?
</question>

<answer>
  The ChatZilla output window is styled with standard CSS.  Messages in the
  output window are nothing more than elements in an HTML table.  Those elements
  have attributes on them which identify who sent the message and what type of
  message it is.  You can then style specific messages using
  <a href="http://academ.hvcc.edu/~kantopet/css/index.php?page=css+attr+selectors&amp;parent=css+syntax">CSS attribute selectors</a>.
  <p/>
  Read the comment at the top of
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/motifs/output-base.css">output-base.css</a>
  for more information.  Once you've got a handle on that, check out the source
  for the
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/motifs/output-dark.css">Dark</a>
  and 
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/motifs/output-light.css">Light</a>
  motifs (pay particular attention to the way they import the base motif.)
   The
  <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/style.html">Stylin' ChatZilla</a>
   document is a bit dated, but might offer some insight as well.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="make-faces">
<question>
  How do I make a faces motif for my channel/network?
</question>

<answer>
  If you have a bit of cgi-enabled server space and some spare bandwidth, you
  might try using the scripts located in
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/facesrv/">chatzilla/facesrv/</a>
  on hacksrus.  In that tarball, you'll find three scripts:
  <ul>
    <li><tt>makefaces.pl</tt> creates three faces motifs
      (<tt>output-default-faces.css</tt>,
       <tt>output-dark-faces.css</tt>, and <tt>output-light-faces.css</tt>),
      based on images in a particular directory.
    </li>
    <li><tt>addface.pl</tt> is a CGI that accepts an image file via the web,
      and scales it to an appropriate size, converts it to a png, and then
      runs <tt>makefaces.pl</tt>.
    </li>
    <li><tt>faces.pl</tt> is a CGI that can be used to display all of the
      faces on a single web page.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="output-window">
<question>
  Can I make my own HTML file for the output window?
</question>

<answer>
  <warning>There are currently permission problems relating to custom output
    windows, which involve granting special permissions to all local files and
    including some extra code in the output window itself. Unless you are
    really intimate with codebase principals and their use in Mozilla, it is
    advised you don't try to do this.
  </warning>
  <p>Yes.  By replacing the HTML file ChatZilla displays messages in, you can
    make an unlimited number of customizations for the output window. Because
    the output window has access to all of Mozilla, including XPCOM, it can
    do anything ChatZilla can.  This includes redisplaying information
    scraped from the web, state stored in a bot of some sort, or just about
    anything else. For security reasons these replacement ``output windows''
    cannot be remotely located, and must instead be
    <a href="#install-script">installed</a> by users.
  </p>
  <p>The ``outputWindowURL'' pref is used to select the output window file
    to use for a particular network, channel, or user.  See the
    default
    <a href="view-source:http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/output-window.html">output-window.html</a>
    and
    <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/output-window.js">output-window.js</a>
    for more clues.
  </p>
  <p>This hasn't gotten much use as of yet, but the basic idea is to make your
    own <b>output-window.html</b>, but use the stock <b>output-window.js</b>.
    JavaScript
    customizations should go in a new .js file, included in a &lt;script&gt;
    tag in your custom output-window.html.
  </p>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="scripts">
<question>
  How do I script ChatZilla?
</question>
<answer>
  With JavaScript!  ChatZilla is written entirely in JavaScript, and has
  provisions for loading (and unloading) plugins written in same.  Because
  ChatZilla itself is written in JavaScript, plugins are not much more than
  additional ChatZilla code, and can therefore do anything ChatZilla can do.
  <p/>
  There are a number of convenience functions for adding new commands, new
  menus, or just hooking existing events.  While these techniques have yet
  to be well documented, there are a number of samples available.  The
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/scripts/sample/init.js">sample plugin</a>
  shows the basics of how to define new commands and place them in menus.
  <p/>
  The application framework that ChatZilla is built on was originally developed
  for <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/venkman/">Venkman</a>.  I gave
  a techtalk during that time that described how to use the framework to extend
  Venkman.  The
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/venkman/techtalk/">notes</a> are
  online, and may prove useful.
  <p/>
  The source of ChatZilla itself provides a number of examples of how to use
  the framework:
  <ul>
    <li>
      For a list of default menus in ChatZilla, see
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/menus.js">menus.js</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      For examples of the default commands, see
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/commands.js">commands.js</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Default preferences are defined in
      <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/prefs.js">prefs.js</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Internationalizable command strings, such as help text, UI labels, and
      parameter lists are stored in 
      <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/locale/en-US/chatzilla.properties">chatzilla.properties</a>.
    </li>
  </ul>
  
  <tip>If you find yourself stuck, drop in on
  <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/chatzilla">#chatzilla</a> - there are a number
  of people in there who have experimented with scripting, and may well be able
  to help directly, or give good pointers to learning yourself.</tip>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="install-script">
<question>
  How do I install a third party script in ChatZilla?
</question>
<answer>
  <ol>
    <li>Firstly, you must find out where ChatZilla looks for scripts. This can
      be done as follows:
      <input>
        /pref profilePath
      </input>
      <output>
        Preference profilePath is "C:\Documents and Settings\James\Application Data\Mozilla\ChatZilla\Profiles\w58z18i7.default\chatzilla".
      </output>
      <note>If the above command outputs an empty value, you will need to do
        <tt>/pref profilePath -</tt> instead, to fix it.
      </note>
    </li>
    <li>Go into the directory displayed by ChatZilla, then into the
      <tt>scripts</tt> subdirectory. This is where ChatZilla looks for scripts
      to load when starting.
    </li>
    <li>Create a new subdirectory for the script - name it something related
      to the script. ChatZilla doesn't care what you call it.
    </li>
    <li>Save the script into this new subdirectory. If the script came with
      multiple files, put them all in here. Make sure that a file called
      <tt>init.js</tt> exists, or ChatZilla wont load the script!
    </li>
    <li>Restart ChatZilla.
    </li>
  </ol>
  <tip>If you're having problems getting a script to load, it may be having
    errors during initialization.  To check this, open the client view with the
    <code>/client</code> command, then tick <menu>IRC<submenu/>Open This
    Tab At Startup</menu>, and restart ChatZilla. Any errors that occur
    loading scripts during startup will be displayed on this new view.
  </tip>
  <note>ChatZilla will also load <tt>chatzilla/scripts/init.js</tt> at startup,
    if it exists.  It is recommended that you use this for one-off, personal
    scripts, or for any script that might need to make sure it is the first
    one loaded.
  </note>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="prefs">
<question>
  How do I tweak the rest of the preferences?
</question>

<answer>
  There are two ways.  The first, and easiest, is to use the prefs dialog,
  accessible from <menu>ChatZilla<submenu/>Preferences</menu>.
  
  If you want more control, and access to "hidden" prefs, use the
  <tt>/pref</tt> command, or one of the variants.  Type <tt>/pref</tt> to
  list all of the global preferences.
  <p/>
  You may provide a pref name, or just the first few letters of a pref name, to
  see the current value of matching preferences.  To change a preference, type
  <tt>/pref pref-name new-value</tt>.  To edit a preference for a specific
  network, channel, or user, use <tt>/network-pref</tt>, <tt>/channel-pref</tt>,
  or <tt>/user-pref</tt>.  There are network, channel, and user specific
  variants of the <tt>/motif</tt> command as well.
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="docs">
<title>Documentation and Resources</title>

<entry id="how-faces">
<question>
  How do the faces motifs work?
</question>

<answer>
  The
   <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/faces.pl">faces motifs</a>
  are nothing more than css files.  They work just like any other
  <a href="#make-motif">motif</a>, except they insert images before certain
  nicknames.  Those images are located on a web server, along with the CSS
  files.  If your CSS-fu is strong, you may want to take a look at the
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/motifs/output-default-faces.css">source</a>.  
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="moredocs">
<question>
  Where is the rest of the documentation?
</question>

<answer>
  <ul>
    <li>
      The
      <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/">ChatZilla Home Page</a>
      is the hub of all things ChatZilla.
    </li>
    <li>
      The
      <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/">ChatZilla Development Page</a>
      contains installable development versions of ChatZilla, and provides
      up-to-the-minute information about ChatZilla development.
    </li>
    <li>
      The
      <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/faq/chatzilla-faq.html">Official ChatZilla FAQ</a>
      is what you're reading right now.  You can also get it in
      <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/faq/chatzilla-faq.xml">XML format</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      Moztips maintains an
      <a href="http://www.moztips.com/index.php?id=7">Unofficial ChatZilla FAQ</a>.
      It's a bit dated, but still has some useful information.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="ng">
<question>
  Is there a newsgroup or mailing alias for ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  The newsgroup is <b>mozilla.dev.apps.chatzilla</b> and can be found on
  the public news server <b>news.mozilla.org</b>.  It is mirrored on the mailing
  alias dev-apps-chatzilla@lists.mozilla.org.  To subscribe, send an email to
  <a href="mailto:dev-apps-chatzilla-request@lists.mozilla.org?subject=subscribe">dev-apps-chatzilla-request@lists.mozilla.org</a>
  with the subject "subscribe".  To unsubscribe, send a mail to the request
  address with the subject
  <a href="mailto:dev-apps-chatzilla-request@lists.mozilla.org?subject=unsubscribe">unsubscribe</a>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="irc">
<question>
  Is there an IRC channel for ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  Of course there is!  The channel is
  <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/chatzilla">#chatzilla</a> on
  <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org">irc.mozilla.org</a>.
  <p/>
    If you are running
    Mozilla and already have
    <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/">ChatZilla</a>
    installed, you can join the channel by clicking on the <b>#chatzilla</b> link
    above.
  <p/>
    If you are new to IRC, please read over
    <a href="http://www.irchelp.org">irchelp.org</a>.
  <p/>
    Please be patient if you join <b>#chatzilla</b> looking to ask a question.
    I'm pretty much always logged
    on to IRC, but that doesn't mean I'm actually looking at the window, or
    even sitting in front of the computer.  If I see your question before you
    leave the channel, chances are I'll answer it.  If you include the word
    ``chatzilla'' in your question, it'll ring a bell on my machine which may
    make me respond sooner.  Please don't abuse that :)  Often times there will
    be other ChatZilla developers and/or users on #chatzilla who may be
    able to answer your question just as well.    
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="more-motifs">
<question>
  Where can I find more motifs?
</question>

<answer>
  The
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/motifs/">motifs directory on hacksrus.com</a>
  has a number of alternate motifs, in addition to the stock motifs.  You can 
  use these motifs by dragging the <code>.css</code> file onto ChatZilla's
  message window,
  or by using the <code>/motif</code> command.
  <p/>
  If you
  have <a href="#make-motif">made your own motif</a>, and would like me to
  serve it here, please say so.
  <p/>
  If you're not sure what a motif is, <a href="#make-motif">go here</a>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="screenshots">
<question>
  Are there any screenshots of ChatZilla doing stuff?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes, &lt;<a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/screenshots/?M=D">http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/screenshots/</a>&gt;
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="add-question">
<question>
  How do I suggest a question for the FAQ?
</question>

<answer>
  Please mention it on the <b>mozilla.dev.apps.chatzilla</b>
  <a href="#ng">newsgroup</a>, or in the <a href="#irc">irc channel</a>.
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="build">
<title>Source Questions</title>

<entry id="source">
<question>
  Where is the ChatZilla source code located?
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla is written
  entirely in <b>JavaScript</b> and <b>XUL</b> and lives in 
  <tt>ChatZilla.jar</tt> in the Mozilla Chrome directory. You can view the 
  source on-line using LXR:
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc">mozilla/extensions/irc/</a>.
  Most of the actual front-end code is in the
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content">xul/content/</a>
  subdirectory, and you'll find the supporting libraries in
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/js/lib/">js/lib/</a>
  subdirectory.
  <p/>
  If you want to change things, you're much better off using a ChatZilla 
  plugin, then you don't need to keep re-applying your changes each time 
  there's a new version. See <a href="#scripts">How do I script ChatZilla?</a> 
  for more information on this.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="localization">
<question>
  How do I make a locale package for ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  A guide has been written on this matter. It can be found
  <a href="http://chatzilla.hacksrus.com/localization.html">here</a>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="report-bug">
<question>
  What do I do if I find a bug in ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <ol>
    <li>Search for duplicates.  You can scan the
      <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;component=ChatZilla">entire ChatZilla bug list</a>
        or
        <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/query.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;component=ChatZilla">search</a> for a particular bug on the list.
    </li>
    <li>If you can't find a duplicate, then please
      <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Other%20Applications&amp;version=Trunk&amp;component=ChatZilla&amp;rep_platform=PC&amp;op_sys=All">file a bug</a>.
    </li>
  </ol>
</answer>
</entry>
</section>

</faq>
