<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="faqs.xsl" type="text/xml"?>

<faq xml:lang="en">

<section id="install">
<title>Installing ChatZilla</title>
<entry id="install">
<question>
  How do I install ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla is currently distributed with Mozilla.
  Download the
  <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/releases/">latest Mozilla release</a>,
  and select <b>Full</b> or <b>Custom</b> when installing.
  <p/>
  If you're running Netscape 7.x, or already have Mozilla installed and simply
  want to add or upgrade ChatZilla, visit the
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/">ChatZilla Development Page</a>.
  <p/>
  <p>
  On all platforms, you will need to restart your browser after installing.
  On all versions of Windows, you will need to exit the quick launch icon on
  your taskbar as well, and on <b>some</b> versions of Windows, you may need to
  restart the operating system.
  </p>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="uninstall">
<question>
  How do I uninstall ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  Mozilla does not have an uninstall feature for XPIs <i>yet</i>.  The following
  manual uninstall procedure is provided with no warranty whatsoever:
  <ol>
    <li>Shut down Mozilla
    </li>
    <li>Rename the files <tt>components/chatzilla-service.js</tt>
        and <tt>chrome/chatzilla.jar</tt> to something else.
    </li>
    <li>Run <tt>regchrome</tt>
    </li>
    <li>If Mozilla starts up fine, everything worked, otherwise, unrename
        everything and give up, or delete the installation and start from
        scratch.
    </li>
  </ol>
</answer> 
</entry>

<entry id="default-ircurls">
<question>
  How do I make irc: urls work with my default IRC client instead of ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  If you are using the Mozilla Suite, you will need to use the uninstall
  procedure outlined above. If you are using Mozilla Firefox, use the 
  following steps (you will need at least version 0.9.50):
  <ol>
  	<li>Open the Options dialog from the Tools menu.
  	</li>
  	<li>Select the Extensions item on the left of the dialog.
  	</li>
  	<li>Find and select Chatzilla in the list of extensions on the right.
  	</li>
  	<li>Click the Disable Extension button. If the only buttons are
  			Settings and Enabled Extension, Chatzilla is already disabled.
  	</li>
  </ol>
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="start">
<title>Getting Started</title>

<entry id="start-moz">
<question>
  How do I start ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <ol>
    <li>You can start ChatZilla from the <b><u>W</u>indow-&gt;IRC Chat</b> 
      menu in the Mozilla Suite, and with the <b>IRC Chat</b> button you can
      place on Mozilla Firefox's toolbar.
    </li>
    <li>You can also start the browser with the <tt>-chat</tt> command line
      option.  This will launch ChatZilla instead of a browser front end.
    </li>
    <li>You can type an <tt>irc</tt> in the URL bar. Type just <tt>irc:</tt>
      to launch ChatZilla and connect to default channels.  Note that you 
      can bookmark this URL, and file it wherever it to make sense to you.
    </li>
  </ol>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="start-fb">
<question>
  How do I start ChatZilla in Mozilla Firefox?
</question>

<answer>
  If you have ChatZilla 0.9.51 or newer, you can place an <b>IRC Chat</b> 
  button on your toolbar, which will start ChatZilla.
  <p/>
  The only way to start older ChatZilla versions in Mozilla Firefox is via an 
  <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/irc-urls.html">irc: URL</a>.
  Type "irc:" in the url bar to launch ChatZilla and connect to your default
  channels.  You may want to file a bookmark in your personal toolbar to
  make this easier.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="connect">
<question>
  How do I connect to a server?
</question>

<answer>
  Type <tt>/server irc.servername.com</tt>.  You may also pass a port and
  server password to the /server command.  See <tt>/help server</tt> for
  more information.
  <p/>
  ChatZilla allows you to be connected to multiple servers, so unlike some
  other clients, <tt>/server</tt> will not disconnect you from your current
  server.  You can manually do that with the <tt>/disconnect</tt> command.
  <p/>
  ChatZilla comes preset with a few popular irc networks.  Use the
  <tt>/networks</tt> command to list the available networks.  You may click
  on a network name or use the <tt>/attach</tt> command to connect to a network
  by name.
  <p/>
  <a name="attach"></a>
  The <tt>/attach</tt> command accepts an
  <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/irc-urls.html">irc: URL</a>
  as a parameter.  You may omit the <tt>irc://</tt> prefix, however.  This
  can be used to connect to a network and channel with a single command,
  such as <tt>/attach moznet/chatzilla</tt>, or
  <tt>/attach moznet/killer,isnick</tt>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="join">
<question>
  How do I join a channel?
</question>

<answer>
  Once you have connected to a server, you can join a channel by typing
  <tt>/join</tt>, followed by the channel name.  For example, if you want to
  join <tt>#worldchat</tt> on <tt>undernet</tt>, you would first connect
  to undernet with the <a href="#server">server</a> or
  <a href="#attach">attach</a> command, then type <tt>/join #worldchat</tt>.
  <p/>
  If you omit the channel prefix, ChatZilla will prepend a "#" automaticaly.
  <p/>
  The command <tt>/j</tt> comes predefined as an alias for <tt>/join</tt>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="list">
<question>
  How can I list the available channels on a server?
</question>

<answer>
  The <code>/list</code> command can be used to fetch a list of all channels on
  the current network.  On large networks, however, this may take a very long
  time.  On some networks, you'll be kicked off with a message like ``Excess
  Flood'' for doing this.  Adding to the confusion, some networks recognize
  extended <code>/list</code> options for filtering based on number of
  users in a channel, etc.
  <p/>
  ChatZilla also offers an <code>/rlist</code> command, which can be used to
  filter the result list based on the channel name, regardless of the
  server software.  Type <code>/help rlist</code> for more information.
</answer>
</entry>

<!-- 

<entry id="lights">
<question>
  What do the lights mean in the user list?
</question>

<answer>
  
</answer>
</entry>

-->

<entry id="disconnect">
<question>
  How do I disconnect from a server?
</question>

<answer>
  To disconnect from a single server without exiting ChatZilla, select any
  tab associated with the network in question and type <tt>/disconnect</tt>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="hide-ip">
<question>
  How can I hide my IP address from other users?
</question>

<answer>
  You can't.  The way IRC works, your IP address is distributed to every
  user you communicate with.  Depending on where you hang out, and who your
  enemies are, this may or may not be a problem.  In practice, it's not a
  problem for most normal users.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="dcc">
<question>
  How do use I DCC to transfer files with ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla does not support DCC at the moment.  This was a limitation of
  Mozilla itself, but the nessessary code is now there.  See bug
  <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=73257">73275</a>
  for the current progress in implementing DCC in ChatZilla.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="charset">
<question>
  How do I select a character set? (and why can't other user's read my text?)
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla allows you to select character sets at multiple levels.  The default
  character set used by ChatZilla is UTF-8, and it is recommended that you leave
  this setting wherever possible.  This default avoids a number of unsolvable 
  problems, such as how to know what encoding has been used for particular 
  channel names without proir knowledge.
  
  <p/>
  An unfortunate problem with the way IRC works is that international (and 
  most non-US-ASCII) characters cannot be sent without encoding them.  The 
  problem is that there are many, many different character encodings 
  available, and different systems and programs use different ones.  To help 
  alleviate this problem, ChatZilla supports many different character 
  encodings, and lets you select the right one for each channel and server.
  
  <p/>
  If text is showing up with a lot of question-marks (?) or completely 
  unexpected characters (for example, Japanese characters in a Danish channel)
  then it is likely that ChatZilla is not using the same charset as the other
  client.  The table below lists the charset commands available in ChatZilla.
  Each of these commands takes a case-insensitive character set name as a
  parameter.  If a character set is not provided, these commands will display
  the current setting.  If you pass a dash ("-") as the character set name,
  the setting will revert to the default character set.

  <div class="figure">
    <table class="figure-contents" cellpadding="2px">
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/default-charset</code></td>
        <td>
          Selects the default character set for all networks, channels, and
          users.  This charset is used when no other more specific charset 
          preference has been set.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td valign="top"><code>/charset</code></td>
        <td>
          Selects the character set for the current view, and works from all 
          views.  When changing the network charset all channels and query
          views will inherit the value unless it is set on the specific
          channel or query views.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
      Character set commands.
  </div>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="log">
<question>
  How do I enable logging?
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla logging can be enabled at a number of levels.  The most
  straightforward way to turn on logging for a specific view is to
  type <tt>/log on</tt> from the view in question.
  
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <ul>
        <li>To log the current view, type
            <tt>/log on</tt>, type <tt>/log off</tt> to stop logging.
        </li>
        <li>To log all channel views by default, type
            <tt>/pref channelLog true</tt>.
        </li>
        <li>To log all network views by default, type
            <tt>/pref networkLog true</tt>.
        </li>
        <li>To log all query views by default, type
            <tt>/pref userLog true</tt>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>
    Logging related preferences
  </div>

  Note that you may override any of the defaults by using the <tt>/log</tt>
  command on the view in question.
  <p/>
  By default, ChatZilla stores logs in the <tt>logs/</tt> subdirectory of your
  ChatZilla profile path.  Type <tt>/pref logFileName</tt> to see where this
  is.  You may modify the logFileName pref, but it will not copy over your old
  logs.
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="basic-usage">
<title>Basic Usage</title>

<entry>
<question id="nick-complete">
  Does ChatZilla have nickname completion?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  Type enough of a person's nickname to make it unique and press the
  <b>tab</b> key.
  <p/>
  If the name is not unique, ChatZilla will append any characters that it
  has in common with other matching nicknames.
  <p/>
  If you press <b>tab</b> twice, quickly, then ChatZilla will display all
  matching nicknames.
  <p/>
  From network and query views, you can tab complete on any nickname in
  any channel on the same network.  From channel views, only users in the
  same channel will be included in the tab complete operation.
  <p/>
  In addition to nicknames, you can tab complete any channel you are on
  (or have been on) on the same network.  If you attempt to tab complete
  only the character "#", ChatZilla will assume you meant the current
  channel.
  <p/>
  There is a default tab completion for channel tabs.  If you press
  <b>tab</b> on an empty line, ChatZilla will match the last person to
  trigger your <a href="#stalk">stalk</a> function.
  
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">

  Assuming that <i>rginda_home</i> and <i>rginda_work</i> are members
  of the current channel:

  <ol>
    <li>Type <tt>rg</tt> and press <b>tab</b>.  ChatZilla responds by
        completing <tt>rginda_</tt>.  ChatZilla stops completing here, because
        there are two nicknames that start with these characters.
    </li>
    <li>Press <b>tab</b> twice, quickly.  ChatZilla responds by displaying the
        message ``2 matches for &#8220;rginda_&#8221;:
        [rginda_home, rginda_work]''.
    </li>
    <li>Add an <tt>h</tt>, and <b>tab</b>.  If this is the first word in
        the textbox, ChatZilla responds by completing
        ``<tt>rginda_home, </tt>''.  If this is <b>not</b> the first word,
        ChatZilla will leave out the comma.
    </li>
   </ol>

   </div>
    Nickname completion<br/>
  </div>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry>
<question id="cmd-complete">
  Does ChatZilla have command completion?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  It works just like nickname completion.  If the cursor is in the
  first word of the text, and the first character is a forward slash ("/"),
  then ChatZilla will automatically match against commands, instead of
  users or channels.
  <p/>
  You don't actually need to type the entire command name, however.  ChatZilla
  will allow you to shorten the command just enough to make the name
  unique.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry>
<question id="copy">
  Why do some messages appear in the network tab?
</question>

<answer>
  Those messages have been copied there because they matched your 
  <a href="#stalk">stalk</a> list.  The reasoning here is that, if you're
  away from the computer for a long time, important messages might have
  scrolled off the view by the time you get back.  Copying the
  message to the network tab makes sure you don't miss anything important.  It's
  also a quick way to catch up after being away for a while.
  <p/>
  The <b>View</b>-&gt;<b>Copy Important Messages</b> menu item can be used to
  disable this feature.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry>
<question id="timestamp">
  Where are the timestamps?
</question>
  
<answer>
  If you have ChatZilla 0.9.54c or newer, you can have timestamps in the main
  chat view. If you have turned them off, you can turn them on by setting the 
  <tt>timestamps</tt> preferences to <tt>true</tt>. See the entry on 
  <a href="#prefs">tweaking the preferences</a> for how to do this globally, 
  or per network, channel or even query view.
  <p/>
  Timestamps also appear in the statusbar when you mouse over messages.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry>
<question id="stalk">
  What is a stalk list?
</question>

<answer>
  A stalk list is a list of words or nicknames that you want ChatZilla to
  consider important.  Important messages are treated differently than
  normal messages.  For example:
  <ul>
    <li>The message will likely be styled differently in the message window.
    </li>
    <li>If you have ``Copy Important Messages'' enabled, the message will be
        copied to its associated network view.
    </li>
    <li>The channel's tab label will turn red, if it's not already the
        current tab.  
    </li>
    <li>ChatZilla may beep, or play a .wav file.  You can adjust this setting
        through the <tt>stalkBeep</tt> preference.  
    </li>
    <li>The ChatZilla window may try to get your attention.  On some platforms
        this is done by flashing an application icon, on others the window
        may come to the front.  You can adjust this setting with the
        <tt>notify.aggressive</tt> pref.
    </li>
  </ul>
  By default, your nickname is the only entry in your stalk list.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="channel-key">
<question>
  How can I join a channel that requires a key, at startup?
</question>

<answer>
  From the ChatZilla preferences dialog, select the <b>Startup</b> group, add
  a new channel to join at startup, and specify the channel name as
  <tt>channelname?key=keyvalue</tt>.  So, if you wanted to join <tt>#cia</tt>
  with the key <tt>tenet</tt> at startup, you would specify the channel name as
  <tt>cia?key=tenent</tt>.
  <p/>
  <b>Warning</b>: This information is stored as plain text in your preferences
  file.  Anyone with access to your machine will be able to read it.  Do not
  use this method to autojoin if this concerns.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="colors">
<question>
  How do I use color/bold/underline in my text?
</question>

<answer>
  First of all, you must enable the function - this is to help mark sure 
  you really want colors and aren't just out to annoy people (overly 
  colorful text is a big annoyance to many people). It's usually worth 
  making sure the channel(s) you want to use colors with don't mind, 
  as some channels will kick and possibly ban people who use colors.
  <p/>
  <code>/pref outgoing.colorCodes true</code>
  <p/>
  This setting is saved, so you will only need to do it once. To actually 
  insert colors, bold or underline, you need to enter <tt>%</tt> into the
  input box, then you will get a little popup window reminding you what to
  do. Here is a summary:
  <div class="floating-figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td bgcolor="#000000" class="fg-white">00</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c8c8c8" class="fg-black">01</td>
            <td bgcolor="#0000c8" class="fg-white">02</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00c800" class="fg-white">03</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c80000" class="fg-white">04</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c8c800" class="fg-black">05</td>
            <td bgcolor="#c800c8" class="fg-black">06</td>
            <td bgcolor="#ffb000" class="fg-black">07</td>
          </tr><tr>
            <td bgcolor="#ffff00" class="fg-black">08</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00ff00" class="fg-black">09</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00c8c8" class="fg-black">10</td>
            <td bgcolor="#00ffff" class="fg-black">11</td>
            <td bgcolor="#0000ff" class="fg-white">12</td>
            <td bgcolor="#ff00ff" class="fg-white">13</td>
            <td bgcolor="#808080" class="fg-white">14</td>
            <td bgcolor="#989898" class="fg-white">15</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </div>
    Color Chart
  </div>
  <ul>
    <li><b>%U</b> - toggle underline</li>
    <li><b>%B</b> - toggle bold</li>
    <li><b>%R</b> - swaps foreground and background colors</li>
    <li><b>%O</b> - reverts colors to defaults</li>
    <li><b>%C</b> - sets the text color</li>
    <li><b>%%</b> - putting two percent characters before <b>U</b>,
      <b>B</b>, <b>R</b>, <b>O</b> or <b>C</b> stops ChatZilla doing
      anything special with it, so you can still say "%C" by 
      typing <b>%%C</b>.</li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="customizing">
<title>Customizing ChatZilla</title>
<entry>
<question id="nick">
  How do I set my nickname?
</question>

<answer>
  When you first connect to a server with ChatZilla, you are prompted to enter
  a nickname.  If you would like to change it later, use the <tt>/nick</tt>
  command.  ChatZilla automatically remembers your last nickname for
  each network you connect to.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="desc">
<question>
  How do I set my description?
</question>

<answer>
  Your description is a single line of text that other users will see when
  they request information about you.  Many people use it for their full name
  or web site.  Use the <tt>/desc</tt> command to change your description.  The
  description is sent during the login process, so you must reconnect to the
  server for it to take effect.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="autoperform">
<question>
  How do I ``autoperform'' some commands when I connect to a network?
</question>

<answer>
  Each network has an ``autoperform'' preference which consists of a list
  of standard ChatZilla commands.  You can modify this preference with
  the <tt>/network-pref</tt> command, see the example below.  Be aware
  that if you're using this to automatically ``auth'' yourself with a bot or
  service, that your password will be stored in <b>plain text</b> in your
  preferences file.
  <p/>
  Autoperform commands are executed when ChatZilla successfully logs in to
  a network, regardless of how the connection was initiated.  The commands are
  executed before attempting to join any ``Open at Startup'' channels, and
  before attempting to re-join any existing tabs associated with that network.
  <p/>
  <b>This preference was introduced in
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/">ChatZilla 0.9.41</a>.
  It will not work on older versions.</b>
  <p/>
  <div class="figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
To send a message to a user whenever you connect to EFNet, first select any
tab associated with EFNet, then type:<br/>
<br/>
<tt class="indent">/network-pref autoperform msg WiZ here I am again</tt><br/>
<br/>
You may separate multiple commands with the semicolon (';') character, as
 in:<br/>
<br/>
<tt class="indent">/network-pref autoperform msg WiZ yo; msg mozbot trees</tt>
<br/>
<br/>
    </div>
    Setting up autoperform commands
  </div>
  <p/>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="reconnect">
<question>
  How do I prevent ChatZilla from auto-reconnecting to a network?
</question>

<answer>
  By default, ChatZilla will reconnect to a network if you are forcibly
  disconnected.  On networks with idle time limits, this can earn you a
  temporary ban.
  <p/>
  If you would like to turn this off by default, type
  <tt>/pref reconnect false</tt>.  If you would like to turn it off only
  for a particular network, type <tt>/network-pref reconnect false</tt> from
  any tab associated with the network in question.
  <p/>
  Note that if you change the default to <tt>false</tt>, you can still
  override specific networks with the <tt>/network-pref</tt> command.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="rejoin">
<question>
  How do I make ChatZilla auto-rejoin a channel when I'm kicked?
</question>

<answer>
  By default, ChatZilla will no try to rejoin a channel if you are kicked 
  from it. You can turn this on globally using <tt>/pref autoRejoin true</tt>,
  or <tt>/channel-pref autoRejoin true</tt> to turn it on only for the 
  current channel (see <a href="#prefs">tweaking the preferecnes</a> for more
  details).
  <p/>
  You may want to be careful on which channels you enable this, as some bots
  and channel operators will ban people who auto-rejoin when kicked.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="font-size">
<question>
  How do I set the font size?
</question>

<answer>
  <div class="floating-figure">
    <div class="figure-contents">
      <table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td><i>Control - +</i></td>
            <td>Make text bigger by 2pt</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><i>Control - &#150;</i></td>
            <td>Make text smaller by 2pt</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><i>Control - 0</i></td>
            <td>Reset to browser-default</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </div>
    Summary of Shortcuts
  </div>
  If your fonts are way too large or way too small, it is likely a problem with
  your DPI setting.  Check your display preferences.  If you're set to use
  "System Setting", try one of the pre-defined DPI settings instead.  In
  practice, it seems that "System Setting" is almost always wrong.  Fixing this
  will likely help out with web pages that specify font sizes in points, too.
  <p/>
  If it's not a DPI thing, you can use the options in the menu under 
  <tt>View</tt> &gt; <tt>Font Family and Size</tt>. The options include some
  useful shortcuts (see table to the right) as well as the option to enter a
  size and font name explicitly. <tt>Small</tt>, <tt>Medium</tt> and 
  <tt>Large</tt> are based on the browser's base font size, and the three
  font options (<tt>Serif</tt>, <tt>Sans Serif</tt> and <tt>Monospace</tt>) 
  use the appropriate browser-configured fonts as well.
  <p/>
  For those less inclined to use menus, the commands <tt>/font-size</tt> and
  <tt>/font-family</tt> provide the same functionality. The former accepts the
  text values "default", "small", "medium", "large", "smaller" and "bigger"
  which have the obvious meanings from the menu. The latter command accepts
  the special names "serif", "sans-serif" and "monospace". Both accept other
  values, either the font size in points (pt), or the font family name.
  <p/>
  All these options affect all views in ChatZilla. This doesn't mean you can't
  be awkward and have different sizes or fonts on different views - just use the
  commands described in the <a href="#prefs">preferences</a> entry, and the
  pref names "font.size" and "font.family". For example, if you wanted to make
  the current network use 12pt text instead of the default, you would do 
  <tt>/network-pref font.size 12</tt>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="set-motif">
<question>
  How do I change the color scheme of the message window?
</question>
<answer>
  From the <b>View</b> menu, open the <b>Color Scheme</b> submenu.  ChatZilla
  comes
  with three color schemes, known as "motifs".  <b>Default Motif</b> uses your
  default fore and background colors, and specifies no colors of its own.
  <b>Dark Motif</b> is a dark background on white text, with some appropriate
  colors
  for various message types.  <b>Light Motif</b> is the opposite, using
  white as the background color, and black for message text.
  <p/>
  The <tt>/motif</tt> command can be used to select a CSS file by means of an
  ordinary http: or file: URL.  For example, the command
  <tt>/motif http://example.host.com/cool-color-scheme.css</tt> would be used
  to select the "cool-color-scheme.css" motif from "example.host.com".
  <p/>
  You may also use <tt>/network-motif</tt>, <tt>/channel-motif</tt>, and
  <tt>/user-motif</tt> commands to set a motif for a particular tab, or
  group of tabs.  See the <a href="#multiple-motifs">multiple motifs
  question</a> for more information.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="faces-motif">
<question>
  How do I show faces in ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  There is a motif available that displays pictures next to the nicknames
  of many of the moznet people.  You can find information on
  how to use this motif at the
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/faces.pl">moznet faces</a>
  page on hacksrus.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="timestamp-format">
<question>
  How do I change the timestamp format?
</question>

<answer>
	The timestamp format is controlled by the <tt>timestampFormat</tt> 
  preference, which you can set globally, per network, or even individually 
  on channels and query views (see <a href="#prefs">tweaking the 
  preferences</a>).
  <p/>
  The format string is displayed literally, except for the following 6 
  substrings, which get replaced as follows:
  <ul>
  	<li><b>%y</b> - 4 digit year.
  	</li>
  	<li><b>%m</b> - month number (1 - 12).
  	</li>
  	<li><b>%d</b> - day of the month.
  	</li>
  	<li><b>%h</b> - hour, in 24-hour format.
  	</li>
  	<li><b>%n</b> - minutes.
  	</li>
  	<li><b>%s</b> - seconds.
  	</li>
 </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="multiple-motifs">
<question>
  Can I use different motifs for different channels?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  The <tt>/network-motif</tt>, <tt>/channel-motif</tt>, and
  <tt>/user-motif</tt> commands can be used to choose a motif for a
  particular tab or group of tabs.  For example, you might use a
  <a href="#faces-mofit">faces motif</a> on the moznet network, but a "plain"
  motif for dalnet.
  <p/>
  If you've got some web space (no CGI required) you can publish a
  <a href="#make-motif">CSS file</a> specially tailored to your channel.
  This could be as easy as picking a custom background image and a
  matching color scheme.  (You will also need to host any images.)
  Users can try out your motif by typing one of the <tt>/*-motif</tt>
  commands listed above, followed by the URL to the CSS file on your web site.
  Users may also drag a link to a CSS file into the ChatZilla message area, to
  use that file as the <b>default</b> motif.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="make-motif">
<question>
  How do I make my own color scheme?
</question>

<answer>
  The ChatZilla output window is styled with standard CSS.  Messages in the
  output window are nothing more than elements in an HTML table.  Those elements
  have attributes on them which identify who sent the message and what type of
  message it is.  You can then style specific messages using
  <a href="http://academ.hvcc.edu/~kantopet/css/index.php?page=css+attr+selectors&amp;parent=css+syntax">CSS attribute selectors</a>.
  <p/>
  Read the comment at the top of
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/motifs/output-base.css">output-base.css</a>
  for more information.  Once you've got a handle on that, check out the source
  for the
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/motifs/output-dark.css">Dark</a>
  and 
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/motifs/output-light.css">Light</a>
  motifs (pay particular attention to the way they import the base motif.)
   The
  <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/style.html">Stylin' ChatZilla</a>
   document is a bit dated, but might offer some insight as well.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="make-faces">
<question>
  How do I make a faces motif for my channel/network?
</question>

<answer>
  If you have a bit of cgi-enabled server space and some spare bandwith, you
  might try using the scripts located in
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/facesrv/">chatzilla/facesrv/</a>
  on hacksrus.  In that tarball, you'll find three scripts:
  <ul>
    <li><tt>makefaces.pl</tt> creates three faces motifs
      (<tt>output-default-faces.css</tt>,
       <tt>output-dark-faces.css</tt>, and <tt>output-light-faces.css</tt>),
      based on images in a particular directory.
    </li>
    <li><tt>addface.pl</tt> is a CGI that accepts an image file via the web,
      and scales it to an appropriate size, converts it to a png, and then
      runs <tt>makefaces.pl</tt>.
    </li>
    <li><tt>faces.pl</tt> is a CGI that can be used to display all of the
      faces on a single web page.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="output-window">
<question>
  Can I make my own HTML file for the output window?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  By replacing the HTML file
  ChatZilla displays messages in, you can make an unlimited number of
  customizations for the output window.
  Because the output window has access to all
  of Mozilla, including XPCOM, it can do anything ChatZilla can.  This includes
  redisplaying information scraped from the web, state stored in a bot
  of some sort, or just about anything else.
  For security reasons these replacement ``output windows''
  cannot be remotely located, and must instead be
  <a href="#install-scripts">installed</a> by users.
  <p/>
  The ``outputWindowURL'' pref is used to select the output window file
  to use for a particular network, channel, or user.  See the
  default
  <a href="view-source:http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/output-window.html">output-window.html</a>
  and
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/output-window.js">output-window.js</a>
  for more clues.
  <p/>
  This hasn't gotten much use as of yet, but the basic idea is to make your
  own <b>output-window.html</b>, but use the stock <b>output-window.js</b>.
  JavaScript
  customizations should go in a new .js file, included in a &lt;script&gt;
  tag in your custom output-window.html.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="scripts">
<question>
  How do I script ChatZilla?
</question>
<answer>
  With JavaScript!  ChatZilla is written entirely in JavaScript, and has
  provisions for loading (and unloading) plugins written in same.  Because
  ChatZilla itself is written in JavaScript, plugins are not much more than
  additional ChatZilla code, and can therefore do anything ChatZilla can do.
  <p/>
  There are a number of convenience functions for adding new commands, new
  menus, or just hooking existing events.  While these techniques have yet
  to be well documented, there are a number of samples available.  The
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/scripts/sample/init.js">sample plugin</a>
  shows the basics of how to define new commands and place them in menus.
  <p/>
  The application framework that ChatZilla is built on was originally developed
  for <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/venkman/">Venkman</a>.  I gave
  a techtalk during that time that described how to use the framework to extend
  Venkman.  The
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/venkman/techtalk/">notes</a> are
  online, and may prove useful.
  <p/>
  The source of ChatZilla itself provides a number of examples of how to use
  the framework:
  <ul>
    <li>
      For a list of default menus in ChatZilla, see
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/menus.js">menus.js</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      For examples of the default commands, see
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/commands.js">commands.js</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Default preferences are defined in
      <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content/prefs.js">prefs.js</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Internationalizable command strings, such as help text, UI labels, and
      parameter lists are stored in 
      <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/locale/en-US/chatzilla.properties">chatzilla.properties</a>.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="install-script">
<question>
  How do I install a third party script in ChatZilla?
</question>
<answer>
  ChatZilla searches all subdirectories in your
  <tt>&lt;profile-path&gt;/chatzilla/scripts</tt> directory for files named
  <tt>init.js</tt>.  Any files found there are loaded at startup.  To install
  a script that someone else wrote, just copy it into a file called
  <tt>init.js</tt> in a new subdirectory of <tt>chatzilla/scripts</tt>.  To
  find out where <tt>&lt;profile-path&gt;</tt> is on your system, type
  <tt>/pref profilePath</tt>.
  <p/>
  ChatZilla will also load <tt>chatzilla/scripts/init.js</tt> at startup, if
  it exists.  It is recommended that you use this for one-off, personal 
  scripts, or for any script that might need to make sure it is the first one
  loaded.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="prefs">
<question>
  How do I tweak the rest of the preferences?
</question>

<answer>
  There are two ways.  The first, and easiest, is to use the prefs dialog.
  Select <b>Edit</b>-&gt;<b>Preferences</b>, ChatZilla preferences will be displayed
  under the ChatZilla group.  Unfortunately, there are a few bugs in the pref
  panel.  Some settings, like the text transformation prefs, do not take
  effect until ChatZilla has been restarted.
  <p/>
  If you want more control, want access to "hidden" prefs, or want to set
  network, channel, or user specific preferences, use the <tt>/pref</tt>
  command, or
  one of the variants.  Type <tt>/pref</tt> to list all of the global
  preferences.
  You may provide a pref name, or just the first few letters of a pref name, to
  see the current value of matching preferences.  To change a preference, type
  <tt>/pref pref-name new-value</tt>.  To edit a preference for a specific
  network, channel, or user, use <tt>/network-pref</tt>, <tt>/channel-pref</tt>,
  or <tt>/user-pref</tt>.  There are network, channel, and user specific
  variants of the <tt>/motif</tt> command as well.
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="docs">
<title>Documentation and Resources</title>

<entry id="how-faces">
<question>
  How do the faces motifs work?
</question>

<answer>
  The
   <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/faces.pl">faces motifs</a>
  are nothing more than css files.  They work just like any other
  <a href="#make-motif">motif</a>, except they insert images before certain
  nicknames.  Those images are located on a web server, along with the CSS
  files.  If your CSS-fu is strong, you may want to take a look at the
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/motifs/output-default-faces.css">source</a>.  
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="moredocs">
<question>
  Where is the rest of the documentation?
</question>

<answer>
  <ul>
    <li>
      The
      <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/">ChatZilla Home Page</a>
      is the hub of all things ChatZilla.
    </li>
    <li>
      The
      <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/">ChatZilla Development Page</a>
      contains installable development versions of ChatZilla, and provides
      up-to-the-minute information about ChatZilla development.
    </li>
    <li>
      The
      <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/faq/chatzilla-faq.html">Official ChatZilla FAQ</a>
      is what you're reading right now.  You can also get it in
      <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/faq/chatzilla-faq.xml">XML format</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      Moztips maintains an
      <a href="http://www.moztips.com/index.php?id=7">Unofficial ChatZilla FAQ</a>.
      It's a bit dated, but still has some useful information.
    </li>
  </ul>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="ng">
<question>
  Is there a newsgroup or mailing alias for ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes.  The newsgroup is <b>netscape.public.mozilla.rt-messaging</b> and can be found on
  the public news server <b>news.mozilla.org</b>.  It is mirrored on the mailing alias
  mozilla-rt-messaging@mozilla.org.  To subscribe, send an email to
  <a href="mailto:mozilla-rt-messaging-request@mozilla.org?subject=subscribe">mozilla-rt-messaging-request@mozilla.org</a>
  with the subject "subscribe".  To unsubscribe, send a mail to the request
  address with the subject
  <a href="mailto:mozilla-rt-messaging-request@mozilla.org?subject=unsubscribe">unsubscribe</a>
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="irc">
<question>
  Is there an IRC channel for ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  Of course there is!  The channel is
  <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org/chatzilla">#chatzilla</a> on
  <a href="irc://irc.mozilla.org">irc.mozilla.org</a>.
  <p/>
    If you are running
    Mozilla and already have
    <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/rt-messaging/chatzilla/">ChatZilla</a>
    installed, you can join the channel by clicking on the <b>#chatzilla</b> link
    above.
  <p/>
    If you are new to IRC, please read over
    <a href="http://www.irchelp.org">irchelp.org</a>.
  <p/>
    Please be patient if you join <b>#chatzilla</b> looking to ask a question.
    I'm pretty much always logged
    on to IRC, but that doesn't mean I'm actually looking at the window, or
    even sitting in front of the computer.  If I see your question before you
    leave the channel, chances are I'll answer it.  If you include the word
    ``chatzilla'' in your question, it'll ring a bell on my machine which may
    make me respond sooner.  Please don't abuse that :)  Often times there will
    be other ChatZilla developers and/or users on #chatzilla who may be
    able to answer your question just as well.    
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="more-motifs">
<question>
  Where can I find more motifs?
</question>

<answer>
  The
  <a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/motifs/">motifs directory on hacksrus.com</a>
  has a number of alternate motifs, in addition to the stock motifs.  You can 
  use these motifs by dragging the <code>.css</code> file onto ChatZilla's
  message window,
  or by using the <code>/motif</code> command.
  <p/>
  If you
  have <a href="#make-motif">made your own motif</a>, and would like me to
  serve it here, please say so.
  <p/>
  If you're not sure what a motif is, <a href="#make-motif">go here</a>.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="screenshots">
<question>
  Are there any screenshots of ChatZilla doing stuff?
</question>

<answer>
  Yes, &lt;<a href="http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/screenshots/?M=D">http://www.hacksrus.com/~ginda/chatzilla/screenshots/</a>&gt;
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="add-question">
<question>
  How do I suggest a question for the FAQ?
</question>

<answer>
  Please mention it on the <b>netscape.public.mozilla.rt-messaging</b>
  <a href="#ng">newsgroup</a>, or in the <a href="#irc">irc channel</a>.
</answer>
</entry>

</section>

<section id="build">
<title>Source Questions</title>

<entry id="source">
<question>
  Where is the ChatZilla source code located?
</question>

<answer>
  ChatZilla is written
  entirely in <b>JavaScript</b> and <b>XUL</b> and lives in 
  <tt>ChatZilla.jar</tt> in the Mozilla Chrome directory. You can view the 
  source on-line using LXR:
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc">mozilla/extensions/irc/</a>.
  Most of the actual front-end code is in the
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/xul/content">xul/content/</a>
  subdirectory, and you'll find the supporting libaries in
  <a href="http://lxr.mozilla.org/mozilla/source/extensions/irc/js/lib/">js/lib/</a>
  subdirectory.
  <p/>
  If you want to change things, you're much better off using a ChatZilla 
  plugin, then you don't need to keep re-applying your changes each time 
  there's a new version. See <a href="#scripts">How do I script ChatZilla?</a> 
  for more information on this.
</answer>
</entry>

<entry id="report-bug">
<question>
  What do I do if I find a bug in ChatZilla?
</question>

<answer>
  <ol>
    <li>Search for duplicates.  You can scan the
      <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;component=ChatZilla">entire ChatZilla bug list</a>
        or
        <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/query.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;component=ChatZilla">search</a> for a particular bug on the list.
    </li>
    <li>If you can't find a duplicate, then please
      <a href="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Browser&amp;version=other&amp;component=ChatZilla&amp;rep_platform=PC&amp;op_sys=All">file a bug</a>.
    </li>
  </ol>
</answer>
</entry>
</section>

</faq>
